I read poetry all the time
أنا أقرأ الشعر على الدوام
and write about it frequently
وأكتب عنه بشكل متكرر
and take poems apart
وأفصل القصائد
to see how they work
لمعرفة كيفية عملها
because I'm a word person.
لأنني شخص متعلق بالكلمة.
I understand the world best, most fully,
أنا أفهم العالم بشكل أفضل تماما
in words rather than, say, pictures or numbers,
بالكلمات عوضا عما يشاع بالصور أو الأرقام
and when I have a new experience or a new feeling,
وعندما أتعرض لتجربة جديدة أو شعور جديد
I'm a little frustrated
أكون متضايقا نوعا ما
until I can try to put it into words.
لحين أن أترجمها على شكل كلمات.
I think I've always been that way.
لطالما اعتدت على تك الطريقة.
I devoured science fiction as a child. I still do.
لقد شغفت بكتب الخيال العلمي أثناء طفولتي. وما زلت.
And I found poems by Andrew Marvell
ولقد وجدت قصائدا لأندرو مارفيل
and Matthew Arnold and Emily Dickinson
وماثيو أرنولد وايميلي ديكنسن
and William Butler Yeats
وويليام ييتس
because they were quoted in science fiction,
لأنه تم اقتباس أجزاء منها في كتب الخيال العلمي.
and I loved their sounds
ولقد أحببت أصداءها
and I went on to read about ottava rima
وواصلت قراءتي حول اوتافا ريما
and medial caesuras and enjambment
والتأمل والسرد المتناسق
and all that other technical stuff
وكل تلك الأشياء التقنية
that you care about if you already care about poems,
التي تهتم بها إذا كنت تهتم بالقصائد
because poems already made me happier
لأن القصائد تجعلني أسعد
and sadder and more alive.
وأكثر حزنا وأكثر حياة.
And I became a poetry critic
ومن ثم أصبحت ناقدا للشعر.
because I wanted to know how and why.
لأنني أردت أن أعرف كيف ولماذا.
Now, poetry isn't one thing that serves one purpose
الان لم يعد الشعر هو الشيء الذي يخدم غرضا واحدا
any more than music or computer programming
مثل الموسيقى وبرامج الكمبيوتر
serve one purpose.
التي تخدم غرضا محددا.
The greek word poem, it just means "a made thing,"
الكلمة اليونانية قصيده تعني "الشيء المصنوع"
and poetry is a set of techniques,
أما الشعر فهو مجموعة من التقنيات
ways of making patterns
سبل تكوين الأنماط
that put emotions into words.
والتي تحول العواطف الى كلمات.
The more techniques you know,
وكلما عرفت تقنيات أكثر
the more things you can make,
كلما استطعت فعل الكثير من الأشياء
and the more patterns you can recognize
وكلما استطعت التعرف على الكثير من الأنماط
in things you might already like or love.
من خلال الأشياء التي تستسيغ أو تحب
That said, poetry does seem to be
ذلك القول أن الشعر يبدو
especially good at certain things.
جيدا بشكل خاص فيما يتعلق ببعض الأمور.
For example, we are all going to die.
على سبيل المثال نحن جميعنا سنموت.
Poetry can help us live with that.
الشعر يمكن أن يساعدنا على العيش مع ذلك.
Poems are made of words, nothing but words.
القصائد هي صنيعة الكلمات ولا شيء غير الكلمات.
The particulars in poems are like
التفاصيل في القصائد هي مثل
the particularities, the personalities,
الخصوصيات، والشخصيات،
that distinguish people from one another.
التي تميز الناس عن بعضهم البعض.
Poems are easy to share, easy to pass on,
القصائد سهلة المشاركة
and when you read a poem, you can imagine
وعندما تقرأ قصيدة يمكنك أن تتخيل
someone's speaking to you or for you,
أن شخصا ما يتحدث معك أو عنك
maybe even someone far away
قد يكون شخصا بعيدا
or someone made up or someone deceased.
أو شخصا متوفيا.
That's why we can go to poems when we want to
لذلك نلجأ للقصائد عندما نريد أن
remember something or someone,
نتذكر شيء أو شخص ما
to celebrate or to look beyond death
للاحتفاء أو التعزية
or to say goodbye,
أو للوداع
and that's one reason poems can seem important,
وهذا أحد الأسباب لأهمية القصائد
even to people who aren't me,
وبالنسبة للعامة الذين ليسوا مثلي
who don't so much live in a world of words.
الذين لا يعيشون في عالم الكلمات
The poet Frank O'Hara said,
الشاعر 'فرانك أوهارا' قال:
"If you don't need poetry, bully for you,"
"إذا لم تحتاج الى الشعر فأنت قاسي القلب"
but he also said when he didn't want to be alive anymore,
وقال أيضا أنه عندما كان لا يريد مواصلة الحياة
the thought that he wouldn't write any more poems
فكرة أنه لن يستطيع كتابة القصائد أخرى
had stopped him.
أوقفته.
Poetry helps me want to be alive,
الشعر يساعدني في تقبلي للحياة
and I want to show you why by showing you how,
وأريد أن أخبركم لماذا عن طريق إخباركم كيف
how a couple of poems react to the fact that
كيف أن بعض القصائد تتعلق بحقيقة أن
we're alive in one place at one time in one culture,
أننا جميعنا أحياء في مكان واحد في الوقت نفسه في ثقافة واحدة
and in another we won't be alive at all.
وبحقيقة أننا لن نكون أحياء أبدا
So here's one of the first poems I memorized.
وسوف ألقى قصيدة من أوائل القصائد التي قرأتها
It could address a child or an adult.
قد تخاطب طفلا أو شخصا ناضجا
"From far, from eve and morning
من بعيد، من المساء إلى الصباح
From yon twelve-winded sky,
من السماء ذات الرياح الاثني عشر هنالك،
The stuff of life to knit me
أمور الحياة نسجتني
Blew hither; here am I.
من أسفل هذا الجانب؛ ها أنا ذا.
Now — for a breath I tarry
الآن -لأجل نفس أتوانى
Nor yet disperse apart —
ولا أتفرق إلى أجزاء بعد-
Take my hand quick and tell me,
خذ يدي بسرعة وقل لي
What have you in your heart.
ماذا تخفي في قلبك
Speak now, and I will answer;
تكلم الآن وسوف أجيبك؛
How shall I help you, say;
كيف يمكنني مساعدتك، أخبرني
Ere to the wind's twelve quarters
انجرف إلى أرباع الريح الاثني عشر
I take my endless way."
سلكت طريقتي الغير منتهية."
[A. E. Housman]
[أ. إ. هاوسمان]
Now, this poem has appealed
هذه القصيدة تناشد
to science fiction writers.
كتاب الخيال العلمي
It's furnished at least three science fiction titles,
إنها تحوي على الأقل ثلاثة أسماء لكتب الخيال العلمي
I think because it says poems can brings us news
اعتقد أن القصائد يمكن أن تجلب لنا أخبارا
from the future or the past
من المستقبل والماضي
or across the world,
أو إخبار من جميع أنحاء العالم
because their patterns can seem to tell you
لأن أنماطها تستطيع أن تخبرك
what's in somebody's heart.
ما يوجد داخل قلب شخص معين
It says poems can bring people together temporarily,
إنها تخبرنا أن القصائد يمكن أن تجمع الناس مؤقتا
which I think is true,
والذي أعتقد أنه صحيح
and it sticks in my head not just because it rhymes
وأن القصائد تلصق في عقلي ليس فقط لأنها مقفاة
but for how it rhymes,
بل لكيفية تنظيمها شعريا
cleanly and simply on the two and four,
ممتازة وبسيطة في المقطع الثاني والرابع
"say" and "way,"
"قل" و"طريقة" (يقصد النغم الشعري)
with anticipatory hints on the one and three,
مع تلميحات متوقعة على المقطع الأول والثالث
"answer" and "quarters,"
"اجب" و"رباعيات"
as if the poem itself were coming together.
كأن القصيدة تتجمع وتتنغم من خلال نفسها
It plays up the fact that we die
إنها تتكلم عن حقيقة الموت
by exaggerating the speed of our lives.
من خلال تعظيم سرعة انتهاء حياتنا
A few years on Earth become
قليل من السنوات على الأرض تصبح
one speech, one breath.
خطاب واحد، نفس واحد
It's a poem about loneliness --
إنها قصيدة عن الوحدة
the "I" in the poem feels no connection will last —
كلمت أنا في القصيدة تشعر بأنها تعني عدم وجود اتصال مع الأخرين
and it might look like a plea for help
وإنها قد تبدو كنداء للمساعدة
'til you get to the word "help,"
إلى أن تصل إلى الكلمة "مساعدة"
where this "I" facing you, taking your hand,
حيث أن "أنا" تواجهك، تأخذ بيدك
is more like a teacher or a genie,
إنها كالمساعد أو جني
or at least that's what he wants to believe.
أو على الأقل هذا ما يعتقد الشاعر
It would not be the first time a poet had
إنها ليست المرة الأولى لشاعر
written the poem that he wanted to hear.
أن يكتب قصيدة يريد سماعها
Now, this next poem really changed
الآن القصيدة التالية غيرت
what I liked and what I read
ما أحب وما أقرأ
and what I felt I could read as an adult.
وما شعرت به كشخص ناضج
It might not make any sense to you
إنها قد لا تعني لك شيئا
if you haven't seen it before.
إذا لم ترها من قبل
"The Garden"
"الحديقة"
"Oleander: coral
الدفلى المرجاني "نبات ذات اللون المرجاني"
from lipstick ads in the 50's.
من دعايات أحمر الشفاه في الخمسينات
Fruit of the tree of such knowledge
كثمار الأشجار هذه المعارف
To smack (thin air)
لتلقي (الهواء الرقيق)
meaning kiss or hit.
تعني قبلة أو ضربة
It appears
إنها تظهر
in the guise of outworn usages
في ستار الأعراف البالية
because we are bad?
هل لأننا سيئون؟
Big masculine threat,
التهديد الذكوري الكبير،
insinuating and slangy."
التملق والعامية."
[Rae Armantrout]
[راي آرمانتراوت]
Now, I found this poem in an anthology
الان وجدت هذه القصيدة في مختارات
of almost equally confusing poems in 1989.
القصائد الأكثر إرباكا في عام 1989
I just heard that there were these scandalous writers
قد سمعت أن هنالك بعض الكتاب المخزيين
called Language poets who didn't make any sense,
يسمون ب “شعراء اللغة الذين لا يعنون شيئا "
and I wanted to go and see for myself what they were like,
وأردت أن أذهب لأرى كيف يكونون
and some of them didn't do much for me,
وبعضهم لم يجذبوا انتباهي
but this writer, Rae Armantrout,
لكن هذا الكاتب "ري ارمنتراوت"
did an awful lot, and I kept reading her
فعل الكثير من الشنائع، وأنا واصلت قراءتها
until I felt I knew what was going on,
حتى شعرت بأنني قد عرفت بما يحدث،
as I do with this poem.
كما فعلت مع هذه القصيدة.
It's about the Garden of Eden and the Fall
إنها عن جنة عدن والسقوط
and the Biblical story of the Fall,
وقصة الكتاب المقدس عن هذا السقوط،
in which sex as we know it
بأي جنس كما نعرفها
and death and guilt
والموت والذنب
come into the world at the same time.
أتوا للعالم في نفس الوقت
It's also about how appearances deceive,
أنها كذلك عن كيف أن المظاهر خداعة،
how our culture can sweep us along
كيف أن ثقافتنا قد تذهب بنا بعيدًا
into doing and saying things we didn't intend
إلى فعل وقول أشياء لا نقصدها
or don't like, and Armantrout's style
أو لا تحبها، والأسلوب الآرمنتراوتي
is trying to help us stop or slow down.
يحاول مساعدتنا على التوقف أو الإبطاء.
"Smack" can mean "kiss" as in air kisses,
عبارة "سماك" قد تعني "قبلة" كما في القبلات عبر الهواء،
as in lip-smacking,
كما في تقبيل الشفاه،
but that can lead to "smack" as in "hit"
ولكن ذلك يؤدي إلى "سماك" بمعنى "يضرب"
as in domestic abuse,
كما في الإساءة المنزلية،
because sexual attraction can seem threatening.
لأن الانجذاب الجنسي قد يمثل تهديدًا.
The red that means fertility
الأحمر الذي يعني الخصوبة
can also mean poison.
يمكن أن يعني سمًا.
Oleander is poisonous.
نبات الدفلى سام.
And outworn usages like "smack" for "kiss"
والاستخدام الركيك ككلمة "سماك" لـ “قبلة"
or "hit" can help us see
أو "ضربة" قد تساعدنا على الإبصار
how our unacknowledged assumptions
كيف هي افتراضاتنا الغير مقبولة
can make us believe we are bad,
هل تجعلنا نصدق بأننا سيئون،
either because sex is sinful
أما لأن الجنس خطيئة
or because we tolerate so much sexism.
أو لأننا تحاملنا كثيرًا بناءً على جنس.
We let guys tell women what to do.
نحن ندع الرجال يخبرون النساء ما يفعلن.
The poem reacts to old lipstick ads,
القصيدة تتفاعل مع دعايات أحمر الشفاه القديمة،
and its edginess about statement,
وحدتها عن بيان،
its reversals and halts, have everything to do
انتكاساتها وتوقفاتها، لديها كل شيء لتفعله
with resisting the language of ads
مع مقاومة لغة الدعايات
that want to tell us so easily what to want,
التي تريد إخبارنا بكل سهولة ما نريده،
what to do, what to think.
ما نفعله، ما نفكر به.
That resistance is a lot of the point of the poem,
هذه المقاومة تعبر عن نقاط كثيرة من القصيدة،
which shows me, Armantrout shows me
مما تريني، آرمانتراوت تريني
what it's like to hear grave threats
كيف يشبه سماع التهديدات المميتة
and mortal dishonesty in the language
وخيانة الأمانة في اللغة
of everyday life, and once she's done that,
لكل يوم في الحياة، ولحظة عملها لذلك،
I think she can show other people, women and men,
أعتقد أنها يمكنها أن تري الأشخاص الآخرين، نساءً ورجالًا،
what it's like to feel that way
كيف هو الشعور بتلك الطريقة
and say to other people, women and men
وتقول للأشخاص الآخرين، نساءً ورجالًا
who feel so alienated or so threatened
والذين يشعرون بالنفور الشديد أو التهديد الشديد
that they're not alone.
بأنهم ليسوا وحيدين.
Now, how do I know that I'm right
الآن، كيف أعرف بأنني محق
about this somewhat confusing poem?
عن تلك القصيدة المحيرة إلى حد ما؟
Well in this case, I emailed the poet a draft of my talk
حسنًا في تلك الحالة، لقد أرسلت إلى الشاعر مسودة من كلامي
and she said, "Yeah, yeah, that's about it."
وقالت لي، " نعم، نعم، ذلك ما تعنيه."
Yeah. (Laughter) (Applause)
نعم. (ضحك) (تصفيق)
But usually, you can't know. You never know.
ولكن عادةً، لا يمكنك أن تعرف. ولن تعرف.
You can't be sure, and that's okay.
لا يمكنك أن تكون متأكدًا، ولا بأس بذلك.
All we can do we is listen to poems
كل ما يمكننا فعله هو الاستماع للقصائد
and look at poems and guess
والنظر لهذه القصائد والتخمين
and see if they can bring us what we need,
ونرى إن كان باستطاعتهم إحضار جلب ما نريده،
and if you're wrong about some part of a poem,
وإذا كنت مخطئا عن بعض الأجزاء في القصيدة،
nothing bad will happen.
لا شيء سيئ سيحدث.
Now, this next poem is older than Armantrout's,
الآن، القصيدة التالية أقدم من قصيدة آرامانتراوت،
but a little younger than A. E. Housman's.
ولكن أحدث بقليل من قصيدة أ. إ. هاوسمان.
"The Brave Man"
"الرجل الشجاع"
"The sun, that brave man,
"الشمس، ذاك الرجل الشجاع،
Comes through boughs that lie in wait,
أتت من خلال الأغصان المتربصة،
That brave man.
ذاك الرجل الشجاع.
Green and gloomy eyes
عيون خضراء وقاتمة
In dark forms of the grass
في الأجزاء المظلمة من العشب
Run away.
ركض بعيدًا.
The good stars,
النجوم الجيدة،
Pale helms and spiky spurs,
خوذة هزيلة ومهماز حاد،
Run away.
ركض بعيدًا.
Fears of my bed,
مخاوف سريري،
Fears of life and fears of death,
مخاوف الحياة ومخاوف الموت،
Run away.
ركض بعيدًا.
That brave man comes up
ذاك الرجل الشجاع أتى
From below and walks without meditation,
من بعيد سائرًا بدون تأمل،
That brave man."
ذاك الرجل الشجاع."
[Wallace Stevens]
[والاس ستيفنز]
Now, the sun in this poem,
الآن، الشمس في هذه القصيدة،
in Wallace Stevens' poem, seems so grave
في قصيدة والاس ستيفنز، يبدو شجاعًا جدًا
because the person in the poem is so afraid.
لأن الشخص المذكور في القصيدة خائف جدًا.
The sun comes up in the morning through branches,
الشمس تشرق في الصباح عبر فروع الأشجار،
dispels the dew, the eyes, on the grass,
مبددة الندى، من على الأعشاب،
and defeats stars envisioned as armies.
وتهزم تلألآت النجوم كالجيوش.
"Brave" has its old sense of showy
"الشجاع" يملك معناه القديم من البهرجة
as well as its modern sense, courage.
فضلًا عن معناه الحديث، البسالة.
This sun is not afraid to show his face.
هذه الشمس ليست خائفة من إظهار وجهها.
But the person in the poem is afraid.
ولكن الشخص في القصيدة خائف.
He might have been up all night.
ربما كان مستيقظًا طوال الليل.
That is the reveal Stevens saves for that fourth stanza,
ذاك إلهام ستيفنز حفظ لأجل ذلك أربع مقاطع شعرية،
where run away has become a refrain.
عندما يصبح الهروب ممنوعًا.
This person might want to run away too,
هذا الشخص قد يهرب أيضًا،
but fortified by the sun's example,
ولكن تحصن بمثال الشمس،
he might just rise.
إنه قد يشرق فقط.
Stevens saves that sonically odd word "meditation"
ستيفنز احتفظ بتلك الكلمة الغريبة لفظيًا "تأمل"
for the end.
للنهاية.
Unlike the sun, human beings think.
بعكس الشمس، البشر يعتقدون.
We meditate on past and future, life and death,
نحن نتأمل في الماضي والحاضر، في الحياة والموت،
above and below.
في الأعلى وفي الأسفل.
And it can make us afraid.
ويمكنها أن تجعلنا خائفين.
Poems, the patterns in poems,
قصائد، وأنماط في القصائد،
show us not just what somebody thought
ترينا ليس فقط ما يظنه البعض
or what someone did or what happened
أو ما فعله البعض أو ما حدث
but what it was like to be a person like that,
ولكن كيف هو الشعور أن تكون شخصًا مثل ذلك،
to be so anxious, so lonely, so inquisitive,
أن تكون فضوليًا، وحيدًا، قلقًا،
so goofy, so preposterous, so brave.
أحمقًا، أخرقًا، شجاعًا
That's why poems can seem at once so durable,
لذلك تبدوا الأشعار متماسكة جدًا،
so personal, and so ephemeral,
شخصية جدًا، وسريعة الزوال،
like something inside and outside you at once.
كشيء يدخل ويخرج منك في لحظة.
The Scottish poet Denise Riley compares poetry
الشاعر الأسكتلندي دينيس رايلي يقارن القصيدة
to a needle, a sliver of outside I cradle inside,
بالإبرة، فضية من الخارج، وهشة من الداخل،
and the American poet Terrance Hayes
والشاعر الأمريكي تيرانس هاييس
wrote six poems called "Wind in a Box."
كتب ستة قصائد تسمى "رياح في الصندوق."
One of them asks, "Tell me,
يتساءل في إحداها، " أخبرني،
what am I going to do when I'm dead?"
ما الذي سأفعله عند موتي؟"
And the answer is that he'll stay with us
والإجابة هي أنه سيبقى معنا
or won't stay with us inside us as wind,
أو لن يبقى معنا بداخلنا كالرياح،
as air, as words.
كالهواء، كالكلمات.
It is easier than ever to find poems
العثور على قصائد أسهل بكثير الآن
that might stay inside you, that might stay with you,
قد تبقى بداخلك، وقد تظل معك،
from long, long ago, or from right this minute,
من السابق جدًا، أو من هذه الدقيقة،
from far away or from right close to where you live,
من البعيد جدًا أو من القريب جدًا من معيشتك،
almost no matter where you live.
لا مشكلة أينما كنت تعيش تقريبًا.
Poems can help you say, help you show how you're feeling,
القصائد تستطيع مساعدتك على القول، تساعدك على كيف تشعر،
but they can also introduce you
ولكن يمكنها أبضًا أن تقدمك
to feelings, ways of being in the world,
للأحاسيس، طرق بقائك في العالم،
people, very much unlike you,
الأشخاص، يختلفون كثيرًا عنك،
maybe even people from long, long ago.
ربما أشخاص من الأزمان البعيدة جدًا.
Some poems even tell you
بعض القصائد تخبرك حتى
that that is what they can do.
أن ذلك ما تستطيع فعله.
That's what John Keats is doing
ذلك ما يفعله جون كيتس
in his most mysterious, perhaps, poem.
في واحدة من أغمض قصائده، ربما.
It's mysterious because it's probably unfinished,
هي غامضة لأنها ربما قد تكون غير مكتملة،
he probably left it unfinished,
وهو ربما قد تركها غير مكتملة،
and because it might be meant
وربما قد يكون مقصودًا
for a character in a play,
لشخصية في اللعبة،
but it might just be Keats' thinking
ولكن ربما قد تكون مجرد أفكار لـ كيتس
about what his own writing,
عن كتابته الخاصة،
his handwriting, could do,
خط يده، قد يفعل
and in it I hear, at least I hear, mortality,
وبها قد سمعت، على الأقل سمعت، وفيات،
and I hear the power of older poetic techniques,
وقد سمعت بقوة التقنيات الشعرية القديمة،
and I have the feeling, you might have the feeling,
ولدي الشعور، بأن لديك الشعور،
of meeting even for an instant, almost becoming,
الالتقاء حتى للحظة، أتى تقريبا،
someone else from long ago,
شخص آخر من الماضي البعيد،
someone quite memorable.
شخص لا ينسى.
"This living hand, now warm and capable
"هذه المعيشة، دافئة وقادرة الآن
Of earnest grasping, would, if it were cold
على الاستيعاب، أريد، إذا كانت باردة
And in the icy silence of the tomb,
وفي الصمت المثلج للضريح،
So haunt thy days and chill thy dreaming nights
حتى تطارد أيامهم ويهدئ أحلام لياليهم
That thou would wish thine own heart dry of blood
وتتمنى من ذينك أن يمتلكوا قلبا خاليًا من الدم
So in my veins red life might stream again,
حتى يتدفق الحياة الحمراء في عروقي من جديد،
And thou be conscience-calm’d -- see here it is --
وأنت تصبح مهدئا للضمير --نراه هنا--
I hold it towards you."
امسكها في اتجاهك."
Thanks.
شكرًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)